# Kira Mills

University of Texas at Dallas Richardson, TX (813)416-7956

Kira.Mills@UTDallas.edu

PhD Student using Molecular Dynamics simulations to study the structure, function, and mechanism of membrane transport proteins. Passionate about communication at the teaching, research, and public level, and at improving the accessibility of science and higher education to all communities.

### **Education**

#### 2018 – Present University of Texas at Dallas

PhD – Chemistry & Biochemistry

- Principal Investigator: Dr. Hedieh Torabifard
- Research Area: Computational chemistry to study membrane transport proteins

#### 2013 – 2018 Texas A&M University – Commerce

B.S. – Chemistry, Magna Cum Laude
Principal Investigator: Dr. Bukuo Ni
Research Area: Organic synthesis

## **Experience**

#### 2021 – Present Vice President

Chemistry Graduate Student Association, University of Texas at Dallas

- Planning and organizing events and seminars dedicated to helping new graduate students acclimate to the program and be set up for success
- Working with administration within the department and university campus to improve both the working and personal lives of graduate students
- Promoting diverse voices and viewpoints within the organization

### 2018 – Present **Teaching Assistant**

Physical & General Chemistry, University of Texas at Dallas

- Aiding student comprehension of concepts in both general chemistry and physical chemistry
- Working with instructors and lab coordinator to modify curriculum to improve student comprehension
- Recognizing common student pitfalls and developing preventative measures to implement during class and lab periods

#### 2016 – 2018 Ronald E. McNair Scholar

Texas A&M University – Commerce

- Developed and performed a 10-week research project in organic synthesis
- Attended and presented at several conferences
- Worked to aid understanding of why research is important and what unique struggles underrepresented groups face

## **Publications**

- 1. **Mills, K.R.**, Baglia, R.A., Mitra, K., Tutol, J.N., Ball, D., Page, K.M., Kallu, J., Gottipolu, S., D'Arcy, S., Nielsen, S.O., and Dodani, S.C.. "An activity-based fluorescent sensor for the detection of the phenol sulfotransferase SULT1A1 in living cells", RSC Chem. Biol., 2021, 2, 830-834
- \* This article is part of the themed collections: Analytical methods in chemical biology and RSC Chemical Biology Editors' Choice

## **Presentations**

- 1. Oral Presentation: ACS Southwest Regional Meeting (2021) "Computational Study of CLC<sup>F</sup> F<sup>-</sup>/H<sup>+</sup> Antiporter Protein"
- 2. Oral Presentation: 255<sup>th</sup> ACS National Meeting (2018) "Diarylpyrolinol silyl ether as organocatalyst for asymmetric cycloaddition of  $\alpha,\beta$ -unsaturated aldehydes to 3-hyroxyoxindoles to produce spirocyclic  $\delta$ -lactones in aqueous media"
- 3. Oral Presentation: Texas National McNair Research Conference (2018) "Synthesis of spirocyclic  $\delta$ -lactones by asymmetric organocatalytic reactions"
- 4. Poster Presentation: 14<sup>th</sup> Annual Pathways Student Research Symposium (2017) "Synthesis of spirocyclic  $\delta$ -lactones..."
- 5. Poster Presentation: ACS Southwest Regional Meeting (2017) "Synthesis of spirocyclic δ-lactones..."
- 6. Oral Presentation: TRiO McNair Scholars Showcase (2017) "Synthesis of spirocyclic δ-lactones..."
- 7. Oral Presentation: Gulf Coast Student Success Conference (2016) "Teaching Scientific Writing, Even as a Non-STEM Peer Educator"